Praneeth Vasarla

Hyderabad • praneethvaasarla@gmail.com • +91 9490544108 • <u>LinkedIn</u> • <u>Medium</u> • <u>Website</u>

Career Summary

Experienced data scientist with 3+ years of professional experience who was responsible for modelling complex problems, discovering insights and identifying opportunities through the use of machine learning, business intelligence, data mining and visualization techniques. Solved problems, created operational efficiencies and delivered successfully against high organizational standards by collaborating effectively with internal stakeholders and cross-functional teams.

Professional Experience

Data Scientist May 2020–Present

Trice Systems Private Limited, Hyderabad

- Used analytics and data mining techniques to solve complex problems and drive business decisions.
- Worked closely with internal teams to identify, define, collect, and track key business metrics for products and business processes which resulted in improved work efficiency across internal teams.
- Pulled required data from MySQL database to conduct business analysis, built reports using SQL,
 Python and Excel, built dashboards and metrics using AWS Quicksight to monitor the performance of the business.
- Applied a breadth of tools, data sources and analytical techniques to answer a wide range of high
 impact business questions and presented the insights in concise and effective manner and
 communicated the insights to non-technical audiences.
- Built a search query optimization model using Machine Learning & NLP techniques and deployed on AWS EC2 instance using Flask, Gunicorn3 and NGINX server which increased search to purchase conversion rate by 35%
- Built a Machine Learning model that predicts gender from the name of a customer and deployed it on AWS EC2 instance which resulted in better user experience and reduced customer drop-offs during the onboarding process by 20%.
- Built a bot on Slack, named Lisa, for the internal tech team to manage, track and record the support requests coming from the customer support team, which is currently deployed on AWS EC2 instance.
- Executed quantitative analysis to address the delayed deliveries issue that translated data into actionable insights which ultimately helped to reduce the delayed deliveries by 20%.
- Executed an internal vendor price comparison for similar products using quantitative analysis and NLP techniques which helped the vendors to optimize their prices for better performance.
- Built an Address Normalization data pipeline in Python using Regex which normalizes the ambiguous text input from the user into a standardized address format. This pipeline has been deployed on AWS EC2 instance and is served as an API via Flask application.
- Built and deployed a mailing system which generates several highly insightful reports and e-mails the
 respective reports to the designated stakeholders at fixed times on AWS EC2 instance using CRON
 Jobs which improved the data transparency and influenced several data-backed business decisions.

Data Science Intern

October 2019-April 2020

Ameex Technologies, Chennai

- Worked closely and learnt about what data science is all about in the real world
- Helped the team to build a new solution offering, financial credit risk analysis
- Got trained on MySQL and the BI tool Tableau

Education

Masters in Data Science & Engineering (Pursuing),

Birla Institute of Technology and Science, Pilani (Work Integrated Learning Programme)

Nov 2021 - Nov 2023

BTech Computer Science & Engineering (Specialisation in Data Analytics),

Veltech Rangarajan Dr. Sagunthala R&D Institute of Science & Technology, Chennai

April 2016 - May 2020

Technical Skills

- Database MySQL
- Coding Python
- Data Extraction & Data wrangling Pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib
- Visualization Tableau, AWS Quicksight
- Machine Learning (Linear Regression, Logistic Regression, SVM, Decision Tree, Random Forest, XGBoost etc.)
- Deep Learning (TensorFlow, Keras, ANN, CNN, RNN, GRU, LSTM, Back propagation, Gradient Descent)
- Excel

Additional Skills

- Good business understanding and communication skills
- Proven data leadership skills to lead small teams
- Ability to self-serve, investigate and get the required data
- Ability to identify use cases for the business and create a roadmap for implementing it
- Ability to highlight key takeaways from the data and present actionable insights
- Approaching problems with an entrepreneurial mindset
- Quick Learner